Finding Aid for Michigan Sea Grant Program records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Sea Grant Program records 1969-2005
Michigan Sea Grant Program.
0671 Bimu 2
Established in 1969, Michigan Sea Grant is a joint program of the University of Michigan and Michigan State University. It is part of the National Sea Grant College Program, a network of 30 university-based programs in coastal states across the country. Michigan Sea Grant funds research projects and educational activities related to all aspects of the Great Lakes. The records document the administration, funding, research and educational programming of the Michigan Sea Grant Program.
21 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred to the Bentley Library in June 2000 (donor no. 6502 ) February 2003 and March 2009.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Michigan Sea Grant is one of 30 Sea Grant programs established across the United States to promote the understanding and intelligent use of the Great Lakes and oceans. Originally established in 1969 at the University of Michigan, Michigan Sea Grant began a partnership with Michigan State University in 1972. Michigan Sea Grant addresses Great Lakes issues that directly affect the state's ecosystem health and economic sustainability in an effort to assist Michigan citizens in protecting and enjoying Michigan's freshwater resources.
Michigan Sea Grant provides a range of research and educational programs. The Michigan Sea Grant Strategic Plan mentions a number of program priorities, including the following:
Anticipating Great Lakes trophic change and preparing resource managers with research-based information that will make them effective decision-makers and stewards of Great Lakes fisheries.
Limiting the introduction of new aquatic nuisance species and controlling the spread and reducing the impact of current aquatic nuisance species.
Providing leadership to help communities understand impacts of coastal development and lead efforts that link coastal ecosystem health to sustainable communities.
Promoting coastal wetland health through education, monitoring, and resource sustainability programs.
Creating Great Lakes literacy among Michigan residents, youth, and decision-makers to support stewardship of Great Lakes resources.
These priorities are implemented in various ways, through outreach and education programs, competitive funding for research, and advocacy.
Michigan Sea Grant sponsors a competitive funding program open to researchers at Michigan universities and colleges, which supports investigation of Great Lakes aquatic resources. Researchers employ biological, engineering, and social disciplines to address Great Lakes problems such as maintaining healthy fisheries, alleviating the impacts of coastal erosion, and developing safe and ecologically sound marine engineering technologies.
The program also employs extension agents, who are located in coastal communities around the state. The agents act as liaisons between coastal resource users and the academic research community. They attempt to educate and provide technical assistance to residents, businesses, resource management agencies, and coastal communities on managing Great Lakes resources, creating sustainable coastal businesses, and understanding Great Lakes ecosystems.
Michigan Sea Grant Communications supports the program's outreach and education efforts by providing information and resources about the Great Lakes to decision makers, resource interest groups, educators, and Michigan residents. The department uses media contact, newsletters, and other publications, in order to help Michigan residents understand and participate in Great Lakes issues and programs.
Michigan Sea Grant is managed by a Director and Assistant Director, located at the University of Michigan, and an Associate Director and Extension Program Leader, located at Michigan State University, who guide and coordinate the program's research and outreach activities. In addition to this management structure, a Policy Committee advises the Management Team on policy and program direction and the Michigan State University Extension Service provides administrative supervision of Sea Grant Extension agents.
Michigan Sea Grant is funded through the National Sea Grant College Program, a part of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), in the U.S. Department of Commerce. Federal funds are supplemented with funds from state, tribal, business, and other non-federal sources to carry out programs on a local, state, regional and national level.
The Michigan Sea Grant program maintains an extensive website which includes information on research, publications, and educational opportunities as well as a collection of news articles and a graphics library. The website is available at http://www.miseagrant.umich.edu/
The Michigan Sea Grant record group consists of 21 linear feet of material, which span the years from 1969 to 2005. The record group includes administrative material, budget and project proposals, and research project files which document the program's efforts to conduct research and educate the public on issues related to the use of the Great Lakes. The records have been divided into five series: Administrative Files, Proposals and Omnibus Proposals, Research Project Files, Research Materials and Visual and Audio Materials.
Subjects:
Aquaculture--Michigan.; Coastal changes--Great Lakes (North America); Fishing--Great Lakes (North America); Fisheries--Great Lakes (North America); Great Lakes (North America); Shorelines--Great Lakes Region (North America); Sand dunes--Great Lakes (North America); Water--Pollution--Great Lakes (North America); Water--Resources--Great Lakes (North America); Wetlands ecology--Great Lakes Region (North America)
Subjects-Visual Materials:
Cold--Physiological effects.; Drowning.; Grand Haven (Mich.); Great Lakes (North America); Sea lamprey-Control--Great Lakes (North America); Shipping--Great Lakes (North America); Superior, Lake.; Tawas (Mich.); Water--Pollution--Great Lakes (North America)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series (5.5 linear feet) contains material created by the Michigan Sea Grant office at the University of Michigan and the Sea Grant Extension Service at Michigan State University. Included are reports, "fact sheets" generated by the program, meeting minutes of the Policy Committee, Management Team and staff, information on Michigan Sea Grant-sponsored conferences and workshops and material, primarily correspondence, created by the directors of the program. The series also includes correspondence related to legislation and funding for both the national and Michigan Sea Grant programs. The Site Visits file contains information on the program and its activities that was presented to national sea grant officials sent to review the program. The College Program contains documentation of the Sea Grant College application process as well as student research and program files. Also of note is the Communications Department file, which is comprised of material related to Michigan Sea Grant-produced publications, and educational material and includes an index of publications created between 1970 and 1993. A small addition to the Administrative files received in the 2003 accession is located in boxes 19-21.
  - Reports and Fact Sheets (Box 1)
    - Quarterly Reports 1986 (Box 1)
    - Fact Sheets 1980s, 1990s, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Long Range Planning Document for Michigan Sea Grant Integrated Research Program 1995-2001 (Box 1)
    - Long Range Plan 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Site Visits 1980, 1983-1995 and miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Retreats
      - Annual Retreats 1978, 1982-1991, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Research Retreat 1991 (Box 1)
  - Workshops and Conferences
    - Bluff Slumping Workshop 1977-1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Sea Grant Conference 1992 (Box 1)
    - Celebrate Great Lakes Conference 1987 (Box 1)
    - Sea Grant Week 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Zebra Mussel Conference 1992-1997 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Conferences and Workshops 1980s, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Policy Committee
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1970s, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes 1971-1989, 3 folders (Box 1)
      (cont. in box 19)
    - Meeting Minutes 1990-1993, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Management Team
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1980s (Box 2)
    - Meeting Minutes 1980-1993, 5 folders (Box 2)
      (cont. box 19)
  - Sea Grant Extension/Sea Grant Advisory Service
    - Extension Progress Reports 1979 (Box 2)
    - Work Plans 1977, 1978-1979, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Reports, Proposals, and Awards, scattered dates (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Publications, Fact Sheets, and Clippings, scattered dates (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Commercial Fisheries Newsline 1982-1994 (Box 2)
      - Dockside Lines 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Great Lakes Troller 1980-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - The U.P. Fisherman 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - The U.P. Land and Water News 1980 (Box 2)
      - The Waters Edge 1984 (Box 2)
      - Beaver Island News 1986 (Box 2)
    - Extension Directors' Great Lakes Coastal Zone Manual 1976 (Box 3)
  - Directors' Files
    - Russell Moll
      - Correspondence
        - 1980s (Box 3)
      - Conferences
        - Lake Levels workshop 1987 (Box 3)
        - Zebra Mussels 1993 (Box 3)
        - Saginaw Bay Workshop 1989 (Box 3)
        - Coastal Erosion Workshop 1987 (Box 3)
        - Co-operative approaches to research/heritage resource center 1986 (Box 3)
        - The Oceanography Society Congressional Forum 1990 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous conferences and workshops 1980s, 1980s (Box 3)
    - Alfred M. Beaton 1982-1983
      - General Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Project Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Michael Parsons Correspondence 1990s (Box 3)
    - William Vorus Correspondence 1992-1995 (Box 3)
  - Legislation and Funding
    - Correspondence 1971-1991, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Congressional Testimony, 1980s (Box 4)
    - Letters of Support, 1980s (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous "Limno-Politics," 1980s (Box 4)
  - Communications Department
    - Miscellaneous and background material (Box 4)
    - Index of Michigan Sea Grant Publications (by publication number and subprogram) 1970-1983 (Box 4)
    - Lake Huron Guide correspondence and miscellaneous 1984 (Box 4)
    - Waterproof your Family 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous publications and drafts, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - National Sea Grant College Program-Histories and Publications, scattered dates (Box 4)
    - Budget and Salary Information. 1980s (Box 4)
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Status Program. 1984 (Box 4)
    - Gulliver the Talking Gull 1991 (Box 4)
    - Fish Distribution maps 1980s (Box 4)
    - Formation of Great Lakes Sea Grant Network 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - Sea Grant Twentieth Anniversary 1990 (Box 4)
    - Student Awards and Papers 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Lake Lab (Box 4)
    - U.M. Museum of Art/Sea Grant exhibit "Impressions of the Georgia Coast," 1986 (Box 4)
  - Association
    - Charter Papers (Incomplete) (Box 19)
    - Annual Report 1984 (Box 19)
    - Establishment of the Department of Trade and Industry 1983 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Resolution 1983 (Box 19)
  - College Program
    - College Status Application (Box 19)
    - Site Visits 1989-1991 (Box 19)
    - Program Files 1990-1993 (Box 19)
    - Student Research Awards 1981-1990 (Box 19)
    - Students Supported 1993-1999 (Box 19)
  - Communications
    - Broadcast Time 1984-1986 (Box 19)
    - Development of a Communication Strategy 1973 (Box 19)
    - Meeting Minutes 1992-1993 (Box 19)
    - Press Release 1986 (Box 19)
    - Publications (Box 19)
  - Funding and Budget Materials 1990-1993 (Box 19)
  - General Info (Box 19)
  - Legislation and Funding
    - Acts, Amendments, Bills, etc. (Box 19)
    - Congressional Briefing Documents 1985 (Box 19)
    - Correspondence (Box 19)
  - Great Lakes Press Briefing 1985 (Box 19)
  - Grant Statistics (Box 19)
  - Informational Letters, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Meeting of the International Association for Great Lakes Research 1987 (Box 19)
  - Management Team
    - Administrative Documents 2000 (Box 19)
    - Meeting Minutes 1991-1993, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Meeting Minutes 1997-2001 (Box 19)
  - Policy Committee Meeting Minutes 1997-2001 (Box 19)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes and Notes 1986-1991 (Box 19)
  - Program Assessment Team Visit 1999 (Box 20)
  - Significant Accomplishments 1998-2000 (Box 20)
  - Strategic Planning 1973-1985 (Box 20)
  - Strategic Planning 2000-2005 (Box 20)
  - University of Michigan and Michigan State: 25 Years of Partnership 2002 (Box 20)
- Proposals and Omnibus Proposals
  The Proposals and Omnibus Proposals series (4.5 linear feet)is comprised of Michigan Sea Grant's funding proposals to the National Sea Grant Program, which is part of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) in the U.S. Department of Commerce. The proposals contain overviews and budget information for the program as a whole, as well as project summaries and budgets for specific research projects. Proposals produced after 1970 are usually split into two volumes. The first volume of the proposals generally contains brief project summaries and budget information, while the second volume contains more detailed project descriptions and information on personnel. Later proposals sometimes include a third volume or supplemental or revised proposals. Michigan Sea Grant began calling these documents "omnibus proposals," starting with the 1995-1997 proposals. (Note to researcher: the 2003 accession added material to the Administrative Files and Proposal series. Look for these additions in boxes 19-21.)
  - Miscellaneous Files (Box 5)
    - Pre-proposals 1991-1993 (Box 5)
    - Call for proposals 1986 (Box 5)
  - Proposals to National Sea Grant Office/National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration
    - 1969 (Box 5)
    - 1970 (Box 5)
    - 1971-1972 (vol. 1 and 2) (Box 5)
    - 1972-1973 (vol. 2) (Box 5)
    - 1973-1974 (vol. 1 and 2) (Box 5)
    - 1977-1978 (vol. 2) (Box 5)
    - 1978-1979 (vol. 1 and 2) (Box 5)
    - 1980-1981 (vol. 1, 2 and 3) (Box 5)
    - 1982 (vol. 1, 2, 3 and revised vol. 1) (Box 6)
    - 1983-1984 (vol. 2 and 3) (Box 6)
    - 1984 (vol. 1, 2 and 3) (Box 6)
    - 1985-1986 (vol. 1,2, 3 and revised vol. 1) (Box 6)
    - 1987/1989 (vol. 1, 2 and revised vol. 1) (Box 6)
    - 1988-1989 supplemental proposal (Box 7)
    - 1989-1991 (vol. 1, 2 and revised vol. 1) (Box 7)
    - 1991-1993 (vol. 1, 2 and revised vol. 1) (Box 7)
    - 1993-1995 (vol. 1, 2 and revised vol. 1) (Box 7)
    - 1995-1997 (vol. 1, 2, revised vol. 1 and 2 and enhancement proposal) (Box 7)
    - 1997-1998 (vol. 2) (Box 7)
    - 1998-1999 (vol. 1 and 2) (Box 8)
    - 1999 (vol. 1 and 2) (Box 8)
    - 2000 (vol. 1 and 2) (Box 8)
    - 2001-2003 (vol. 1 and 2, and appendices) (Box 8)
    - (The Proposals and Omnibus Proposals series is continued in box 20) (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous
    (files received in 2009)
    - Action Plan Drafts 1984 (Box 20)
    - Administration 1986 (Box 20)
    - College Program Proposals 1993-1995 (Box 20)
    - College Grant Proposal Charts 1989-1991 (Box 20)
    - Environmental Info Center 1970 (Box 20)
    - Michigan Great Lakes Protection Fund Proposal 1993-1995 (Box 20)
    - Omnibus Proposal 2000-2001 (Box 20)
    - Omnibus Proposal 2002-2003 (Box 20)
    - Omnibus Proposal 2003-2005 (Box 20)
    - RFP (call for papers) 1986 (Box 20)
    - Risk Communication Project 1991 (Box 20)
- Research Project Files
  The Research Project Files series (8.5 linear feet) is closely related to the information in the Proposals and Omnibus Proposals series, and consists of reports, correspondence and other documents related to specific research projects funded by the Michigan Sea Grant Program. The research files generally contain more detailed information than the project summaries found in the Omnibus Proposal series.
  Michigan Sea Grant's arrangement of the material in the Research Project Files has been largely kept intact. The Sea Grant Office had arranged the files loosely in alphabetical order according to "subprogram" or topic, such as Coastal Zone Resources or Toxic Substances. Each study was given an identification number that corresponded with a subprogram. For example, Coastal Zone Resources studies begin with R/CZ, and Recreation and Toxic Substances studies begin with R/TS. In addition to the subprogram information, studies were assigned a number (R/CZ-1, R/CZ-2, etc.) and filed in numerical order. Although the studies are generally in chronological order, there is some overlap, as some studies were conducted over a period of several years while others lasted only a short time. In addition, some of the subprogram and topical headings changed over time, which sometimes led to the numbering process being restarted.
  There is overlap among the various subseries. For example, studies on the coastal zone of the Great Lakes can be found in the Coastal Resources, Coastal Zone Resources, Coastal Processes, and Environmental Studies subseries. In addition, studies of various topics that were funded with money allocated for program development can be found within the Program Development and Program Development Funds subseries. The researcher should be sure to examine the Research Project Files series when searching for studies on a particular topic. A list of abbreviations used in the Research Project numbering sequence follows this scope and content note.
  - Index of Research Projects 1979-1984
    - Index by Project number (Box 8)
    - Index by Subprogram (Box 8)
    - Index by Principal Investigator (Box 8)
  - Aquaculture
    - Subprogram information (Box 8)
    - Aquaculture development program in Michigan (R/A-1) 1983-1987 (Box 8)
    - Effects of Dietary Steroid Hormone Supplements (R/A-2) 1983-1985 (Box 8)
  - Coastal Resources
    - Subprogram information (Box 8)
    - Coastal Engineering and Shore Protection-Coastal Zone Laboratory (R/SD-2) 1973-1977 (Box 8)
    - Coastal Engineering and Shore Protection (MSG-11) 1973-1978 (Box 8)
    - Shore land Planning in the Great Lakes Basin and in Selected Coastal Zones of the United States, (no id number) 1970 (Box 8)
    - Coastal Zone Laboratory-Misc. Publications 1970s (Box 8)
    - Coastal Wetlands in Conflict: A Joint-Space Approach for Assessing the Perceived Utility of Wetlands (R/CW-1) 1979-1981 (Box 8)
    - Public Policies Affecting the Management and Protection of Michigan's Coastal Wetlands (R/CW-4) 1979-1981 (Box 8)
    - Nutrient Cycling and Hydrologic Processes in Great Lakes Coastal Marshes, (R/CW-5) 1980-1984 (Box 8)
    - Wetland Development Options and Strategies and their Relative Environmental Impacts (R/CW-6) 1979 (Box 8)
    - Effects of Lake Levels on Hydrology and Type of Coastal Wetland (R/CW-7) 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    - Sedimentation Accumulation Rates in Three Michigan Coastal Wetlands (R/CW-8) 1980-1981 (Box 9)
    - Avian Response to Wetlands Vegetative Cycles (R/CW-9) 1979-1983 (Box 9)
    - Abundance, Distribution and Ecological Relationships of Larval and Juvenile Fish in the Pentwater Marsh (R/CW-13) 1981-1984 (Box 9)
    - Distribution, Productivity, and Energy Relationships of Adult Fish in the Pentwater Marsh (R/CW-14) 1983-1986 (Box 9)
  - Coastal Zone Resources
    - An Assessment of Michigan's Great Lake's Underwater Park-Historical Preserve Potential (R/CZ-10) 1978-1979 (Box 9)
    - The Impact of Perceptions of the Environment on Leisure Use of Michigan Shoreline Areas (R/CZ-10) 1978 (Box 9)
    - Implementing Remote Sensing Capabilities in the Management of Water and Wetland Resources (R/CZ-11) 1976-1979 (Box 9)
    - An Analysis of Existing Public Access to the Great Lakes Shoreline (R/CZ-13) 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - Investigation of the Availability of the Shoreline Recreation Areas for Utilization by Senior Citizens (R/CZ-15) 1981 (Box 9)
  - Coastal Processes
    - Numerical Modeling of Shoreline Evolution (R/CP-1) 1989-1991 (Box 9)
    - Geology and Stratigraphy of the Lake Michigan Shore and its Influence on Erosion and Stability (R/CP-2) 1989-1991 (Box 9)
    - Paleoclimatic Implications of Lake Holocene Lake Level Fluctuations in the Lake Michigan Basin (R/CP-4) 1989-1992 (Box 9)
  - Coastal Economic Development
    - Shoreline Protection Investment Behavior of Residential Property Owners (R/CE-1). 1979 (Box 9)
    - Evaluation of Low Cost Shore Protection (R/CE-3) 1978-1979 (Box 9)
  - Environmental Studies
    - A Sediment Dispersal Model for Lake Michigan (R/ES-1) 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Geochemistry of the Sediment-Water Interface in Profundal Lake Sediments (R/ES-2) 1987-1989 (Box 9)
    - Immune Response in Great Lakes Fish Eater (R/ES-4) 1988-1991 (Box 9)
    - Causes and Consequence of Cladoceran Dynamics in Lower Michigan: Implications for Recruitment of Forage Fish Species (R/ES-5) 1989-1991 (Box 9)
    - Introduced Invertebrate Predator and YOY Recruitment: Components of Fish Responses (R/ES-6) 1989-1990 (Box 9)
    - Interactions between Juvenile Fish and the Cladoceran Bythotrephes: Behavioral Aspects of Predation (R/ES-10) 1992-1993 (Box 9)
    - Coastal Zone Management and Shore Lands Management (MSG-10 R/CRM-1) 1970-1975 (Box 9)
    - Traverse Bay Shore land Management Project (R/CRM-1) 1971 (Box 9)
    - Public Policy and Institutional Interactions (R/S-PS-1) 1970-1973, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Institutional and Public Policy Gaming Simulation Models (Walrus Simulation) (R/S-PS-2) 1971-1973, 4 volumes (Box 9)
    - Multi-Objective Planning/Evaluation (Research Policy): Great Lakes (R/RP-1) 1984-1985 (Box 9)
    - Fishery Marine Economics and Marketing (R/ME-1) 1980 (Box 9)
    - Great Lakes Video Series, Transportation Video (R/RP-1) 1970s (Box 9)
    - Great Lakes Resource Policy Research, Bulkley 1983-1984 (Box 9)
    - Institutional Arrangements for Great Lakes Management: Past Practices and Future Alternatives (R/RP-2) 1984-1985 (Box 10)
    - Trends and Emerging Issues in Great Lakes Management: A Longitudinal Study (R/RP-4) 1985-1988 (Box 10)
    - Legal, Institutional and Administrative Issues in Hybrid Water Law Systems (R/RP-5) 1987-1988 (Box 10)
    - An Analysis of Great Lakes Salmonid Angler Preferences and Expectancies for Future Fisheries Management Programs in Lake Michigan (R/RP-9) 1988-1991 (Box 10)
    - The Economic Value of Fish Contamination Advisories to Individual Great Lakes Sport Anglers (R/EP-4) 1990-1993 (Box 10)
  - Education
    - Subprogram information (Box 10)
    - Great Lakes Environment: A Curriculum Package (E/GLE-1) 1979 (Box 10)
    - Evaluation of Three Units of the Sea Grant Curriculum Project (R/GLE-2) 1981 (Box 10)
    - Great Lakes Seminar (E/GLE-3, E/GLE-7) 1980-1982 (Box 10)
    - An Assessment of Great Lakes Studies Potential based on User Interest and Priorities (E/GLE-4) 1980-1981 (Box 10)
    - Great Lakes Video Series (E/GLE-3) 1986 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Sea Grant Distinguished Lecture Series (E/GLE-8) 1983-1984 (Box 10)
    - A Great Lakes Short Course for College Teachers (E/GLE-9) 1984 (Box 10)
    - International Dive Rescue Administration and Management Workshop (E/GLE-10) 1984 (Box 10)
    - Conceptual Design of a Scuba System for Recreation, Scientific, and Commercial Divers (E/GLE-11) 1984 (Box 10)
    - Sea Grant Industry Consortium in Offshore Engineering (E/GLE-14) 1985-1987 (Box 10)
    - Development of Interdisciplinary Field Courses in Coastal Engineering and Management and Ecosystems Analysis (E/CD-1) 1975 (Box 10)
    - Organization and Development of an Integrated Aquatic Science Curriculum (E/CCD-1) 1978-1980 (Box 10)